<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Jack Richter-Powell</title>
    <link>https://jrichterpowell.ca/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Jack Richter-Powell</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 20:35:02 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jrichterpowell.ca/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Is functional analysis actually what we want?</title>
      <link>https://jrichterpowell.ca/blog/funcanal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 20:35:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jrichterpowell.ca/blog/funcanal/</guid>
      <description>Is functional analysis actually what we want? Since this is going to be something of an incendiary post, I feel the need to begin with a disclaimer. I am a very early career scientist. My background is mainly in mathematics and theoretical computer science, and I am completely an autodidact when it comes to the physical sciences. So what I&amp;rsquo;m about to say should be read with such context in mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Map Estimation</title>
      <link>https://jrichterpowell.ca/blog/mapestimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 20:35:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jrichterpowell.ca/blog/mapestimation/</guid>
      <description>Estimating Monge Maps Kantorovich relaxes Monge If you look in a modern treatment of optimal transportation, you will likely find the problem defined as something like $$ W_c(\mu,\nu) = \inf_{\pi \in \Pi(\mu,\nu)} \int_{X \times Y} c(x,y) d\pi $$ This is the modern definition of the problem, where we model the objective as finding the minimum cost coupling between $\mu$ and $\nu$. But this is not the original formulation of the problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things that do not work: Part 1</title>
      <link>https://jrichterpowell.ca/blog/ttdnw1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 20:35:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jrichterpowell.ca/blog/ttdnw1/</guid>
      <description>Prelude In this series I&amp;rsquo;m going to detail some interesting ideas I tried in my research that didn&amp;rsquo;t pan out. By doing so I hope to help other people avoid wasting time on the same things I did. Perhaps they will even realize that something here is not a waste of time and do something cool with it.
Definitions One of my areas of interest is Optimal Transportation. The curious reader can no doubt find a better expose of these ideas on Wikipedia or in one of many books, but the gist is the following: we take some Polish metric space $X$, two probability measures $\mu, \nu \in \mathcal{P}(X)$, and a cost function $c : X \times X \rightarrow \mathbb{R}$.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
